74. A Chinese Legend Lao Tzu is something of a legendary figure
in Chinese culture. He is known as the father of Taoism and the author of the philosophy's
central text, the Dao De Jing. Some of the stories told about Lao Tzu are pretty incredible.
It's said that he remained in his mother's womb for 81 years, and when he was finally
born, he came out a grown man with a full grey beard and long ears. We can be fairly
certain that this story is fanciful, but the facts of the real Lao Tzu's life still remain
a mystery. The first biography of Lao Tzu was written several centuries after he is
thought to have lived. It is included in The Records of the Grand Historian, written in
the first century BC. According to the records, Lao Tzu was a librarian at the Royal Court
of Zhou and a contemporary of Confucius. As the state of Zhou began to break down, however,
Lao Tzu decided to leave. At the entrance to a mountain pass, he gave a guard a book
that revealed the secrets of living a good life, the Dao De Jing. However, in addition
to this story, two other conflicting accounts of Lao Tzu's life are given in the records.
This has caused a lot of confusion, leaving people unsure which Lao Tzu was the real
one. Many modern scholars doubt whether Lao Tzu actually existed at all. The Dao De Jing,
they suggest, may actually be a collection of the teachings and ideas of various ancient
Chinese thinkers. For many followers of Daoism, however, this is all beside the point. The
truth of the teachings, they say, is what really matters, not the man said to be behind them.